<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Abstract of the unnatural rebellion and barbarous massacre of the Protestants in the kingdom of Ireland in the year 1641 collected from the most authentick copies.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A24038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5978</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11490406</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11490406</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47823</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A24038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47823)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Abstract of the unnatural rebellion and barbarous massacre of the Protestants in the kingdom of Ireland in the year 1641 collected from the most authentick copies.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Massacres --  Ireland.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47823:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47823:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ABSTRACT OF THE Unnatural REBELLION AND <hi>Barbarous Maſſacre</hi> OF THE PROTESTANTS, In the KINGDOM of IRELAND, In the Year 1641.</p>
            <p>Collected from the moſt Authentick Copies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Janemay</hi> in <hi>Queens-head-alley</hi> in <hi>Pater-noſter-Rowe,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:47823:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47823:2"/>
            <head>AN ABSTRACT OF THE Unnatural REBELLION, and Barbarous MASSACRE of the PROTESTANTS in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>IRELAND,</hi> in 1641.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE implacable Rancour and reſtleſs At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of thoſe in Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> tho they have in all Ages diſplay'd themſelves in the moſt bloody Characters, and have had the barbarous Effects of depopulating Regions, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys and Kingdoms, by Maſſacres, Sword and Fire, in order to the ſetting up and eſtabliſhing their Religion, by deſtroying the Lives and Properties of thoſe of different perſwaſions: Yet perhaps amongſt all their Efforts of that Kind, none have deſerved greater ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence, nor given a blacker Teſtimony of their Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, than the barbarous and bloody <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion, which brake out in the Year 1641. and was carried on with that Rage and Violence, that it laid almoſt all the parts of that deplorable Countrey in Blood and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, depriving by a moſt horrid <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> above two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand Perſons, of all Ages, Sexes, and Qualities,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47823:3"/>of their deareſt Lives: Leaving Children without Parents, Wives deprived of their Husbands, and Husbands robb'd of their Wives; ſometimes without diſtinction burying whole Families in the ſame Fate. And though there be many Hiſtories of large Volumes, that have Chronicled this Affair, to be ſtill kept alive in the Memories of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, yet it muſt not be accounted a Work improper at this time, to remarque ſome of the moſt important and beſt atteſted Paſſages relating thereunto. This little Collection preſents you with nothing but what comes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Hands of the Great Miniſters of State, and thoſe which at that time had a ſhare in the management of the publick Affairs, and Adminiſtration of that unhappy Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Prieſts and others of that Communion, of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation, have not been wanting to decrie, and as much as in them lies, to blaſt all Evidences of that Kind, and have taken all occaſions to Remonſtrate the Preſſures which they pretend to have ſuffered under the then Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that Kingdom, and ſpare not to term it <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical:</hi> They intimate as if their Caſe were like that of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and equal to thoſe Perſecutions for Religion in the Primitive Times.</p>
            <p>In a Remonſtrance of Grievances preſented to his then Majeſty, in behalf of the Catholicks of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and given in to his Majeſties Commiſſioners at <hi>Trime,</hi> the 17 of <hi>March,</hi> 1642. they Expreſs themſelves to this purpoſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat only ſome Catholicks, conſidering the deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and deſperate Condition they were in, and apprehending the Plots laid to Extinguiſh their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Nation, did take Arms in the North, in Maintenance of their Religion, and for the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Life, Liberty and Eſtate, together with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47823:3"/>Rights, and that the Lords and Gentlemen dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within the Engliſh Pale, were likewiſe by the great Rigour and ſeverity uſed by the State towards them, inforced to take up Arms in their own defence.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>This is the language of that Remonſtrance, whereby they endeavour to caſt the Odium of their infamous Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Butcheries upon his then Majeſty, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Officers of State within that Kingdom; of which there needs no other Confutation, than a true and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Relation of the beginning and Progreſs of that Rebellion.</p>
            <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> was brought in ſubjection to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> by the victorious Arms of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, the beginning of whoſe Conqueſts bear Date from the year of our Lord, 1172. The Towns and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages were contemptible, their Buildings ſo poor, that when the King arrived at their chief City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> he ſet up a Long Houſe made of ſmoothed Wattles, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of their Countrey, and therein kept his <hi>Chriſtmaſs;</hi> finding there no place fit for his Reception and Entertainment. The Inhabitants were as uncultivated as their Lands, being generally void of all manner of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, govern'd by no ſettled Laws, but living like beaſts of Prey, biting and devouring one another; without any reaſonable Conſtitutions for determining of their Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or to fence them againſt open Force and Violence: Murthers, Rapes, and the moſt notorious Robberies, and other Acts of Inhumanity and Barbariſm, raging amongſt them without Controul or means of Redreſs. For the firſt Century almoſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> kept themſelves in Bodies di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and ſeparate from the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> not ſuffering them to inhabit or mix amongſt them, but in after-times by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees they admitted them into a fatal familiarity, which polluted them with their beaſtly Cuſtoms and Manners; for prevention of which, in the times of that moſt excellent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47823:4"/>Prince, <hi>Edward</hi> the third, many good and wholſome Laws were Enacted. Notwithſtanding which, they have not ſail'd at all times to Riſe up and imbrue their hands in the Blood of their Engliſh Neighbours; ſo that <hi>Ireland</hi> hath for a long time been a true <hi>Aceldama,</hi> or Field of Blood, and a devouring Sepulchre of the Engliſh Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>For by the Hiſtories of thoſe times, we cannot find that there was any ſettled Peace or good Eſtabliſhment, from the firſt coming over of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> until the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> which contain'd above three hundred and eighty years; during the greateſt part of which time, they were in Perpetual Troubles and Combuſtions, being extreamly Haraſs'd and over-worn with Miſery: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon that Bleſſed Queen, even in the beginning of her Reign, ſent over Prudent and Religious Governours, to advance the Work of Reformation; and enacted many more wholſome Laws againſt the Barbarous Cuſtoms of the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> Notwithſtanding which Care, and all the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of that wiſe Princeſs, ſtill there was one Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on breaking out upon the Neck of another, even amidſt their repeated Submiſſions and pretended Obedience to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crown; which occaſion'd her to ſend over a Royal Army under the Conduct of her moſt Renown'd and Choice <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commanders. Nevertheleſs it was not without great difficulty and Effuſion of much <hi>Engliſh</hi> Blood and Treaſure, that that Glorious work of redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Traitor <hi>Tyrone,</hi> was accompliſhed. The calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of that War, and the raging of a Famine, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced that Kingdom to a deplorable Condition, in the daies of King <hi>James</hi> the firſt; who ſeized the ſix Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties within the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> which had belonged to the Rebels; ſome part of which were reſerved to gratifie the well-affected Natives, and the reſt diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in certain Proportions amongſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; who ſettled themſelves, and many of their Families, in thoſe parts, laying the Foundations of ſome good
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47823:4"/>Towns, incompaſſed with Stone Walls; raiſing ſeveral Caſtles and Houſes of ſtrength in the parts of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to the great Comfort, and ſecurity of the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Inhabitants; who with great coſt and much Induſtry cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated the Land, and introduced Civility amongſt the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; the whole Kingdom began exceedingly to flouriſh, the People to multiply and increaſe, and the very <hi>Iriſh</hi> themſelves ſeemed ſatisfied with the Tranquility they enjoyed.</p>
            <p>Upon the Acceſſion of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt to the Crown, the Affairs of <hi>Ireland</hi> look with a more calm and benign Face than in Times paſt; many Applications from the Popiſh Nobility and Gentry, for the Redreſs of their Grievances, were with great Clemency received, and with great Moderation recommended to the Care of the then two Houſes of Parliament ſitting at <hi>Dublin.</hi> The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks were permitted to the private Exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, with great Freedom; they had their Orders of Biſhops, Vicars, Prieſts and Nuns permitted amongſt them; and by the Inter-Marriages of the Engliſh, with ſome of the better refin'd Natives, all things preſented as if inclin'd to Amity: the advantages they received by the Engliſh Improvements and Commerce, cauſed many of the Native Gentry and others, to diſplace their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tenants, and ſet their Lands to the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> of which they found the Benefit by a great advance of their Rents and Securities: ſo ſerene and full of Lenity was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Government, that the late Iriſh Army raiſed for the Invaſion of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> were Peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly disbanded, and their Arms and Munition laid up in his Majeſties Stores in the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin;</hi> there ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be no more remains of former Diſorders, nor was there any more noiſe of War heard. In this great calm the Engliſh were in a profound Security, under the Hopes of a Bleſſed Peace. All ſate pleaſantly enjoying the Fruits of their Labours, without any Apprehenſions of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Storm, when on the twenty third of <hi>October,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:47823:5"/>One thouſand ſix hundred forty one, brake out that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Rebellion, and univerſal Defection and Revolt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in not only the Native <hi>Iriſh,</hi> but almoſt all the old <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> that adhered to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> were generally concerned. It would be a large Task to trace out the Progreſs of the Rebellion, ſo execrable in its ſelf, ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to God, and the whole World, as no Age, no King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor People can match the horrid Cruelties, the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Murders, that have been almoſt numberleſs, as well as without Mercy, committed upon the Engliſh and Proteſtant Inhabitants throughout the Land. And this carried on with ſuch a deep reſervedneſs and Secreſie, as is enough to beget Admiration: for it could not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that any Engliſh man (beſides the uncertain Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption which Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had of a Commotion to be raiſed in the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> about a fortnight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this dreadful Rebellion broke forth;) I ſay, that any Engliſh, man had Notice, or the leaſt Apprehenſions of it. It's true, the ſaid Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> upon his firſt conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſomething was hatching amongſt the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> did write a Letter to the Lords Juſtices and Council, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the eleventh of <hi>October,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred forty one. Wherein he gave them Notice of the great reſort made to Sir <hi>Phelim Oneal,</hi> in the County of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and likewiſe to the Houſe of the Lord <hi>Mac-Guire</hi> in the County of <hi>Fermanagh,</hi> and that by Perſons much ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be fit Inſtruments for Miſchief; as alſo that the ſaid Lord <hi>Mac Guire,</hi> had lately made ſeveral Journeys into the <hi>Pale,</hi> and other places: And had ſpent much time in writting Letters, and ſending Diſpatches abroad. The Lords upon receipt of thoſe Letters from Sir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Cole,</hi> required him to be very Vigilant, and uſe his utmoſt Diligence to find out the occaſion of thoſe meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and to give them the moſt ſpeedy Advertiſement thereof, or of any other matter that might tend to the ſervice of the State. The twenty third of <hi>October,</hi> was the day appointed for ſeizing the City and Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:47823:5"/>and for murdering the Lords Juſtices, and Council of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the reſt of the Proteſtants, and to ſeize upon all the Caſtles, Forts, Sea-Ports and Strengths, that were in the hands of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> Notice hereof was brought to the Lord Juſtice <hi>Parſons,</hi> the Evening before, by <hi>Owen O Connally,</hi> a Perſon of meer <hi>Iriſh</hi> Extraction: His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip gave little credit to it at firſt, as proceeding from an obſcure Perſon, and one who at that time ſeemed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed with Liquor; but however the Lord <hi>Parſons</hi> gave him order again to go to <hi>Mac Mahon,</hi> and to get out of him, as much certainty of the Plot, and as many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, as he could; charging him to return unto him that Evening, with an Account of what farther par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars he could get.</p>
            <p>Immediately ſtrict Orders were given to the Conſtable of the Caſtle to have the Gates thereof well guarded, as alſo to the Maior and Sheriffs of the City, to have ſtrong Watches ſet upon all the parts of the ſame, and to ſtop all Strangers. About ten that night they found the ſaid <hi>Connally</hi> ſeized by the Watch, and carried to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and from thence they brought him to the Lord <hi>Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces</hi> Houſe; where upon Examination, upon Oath, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that finding Col. <hi>Hugh Oge Mac-Mahon,</hi> at the Lord <hi>Mac Guire</hi>'s Lodging, the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> told him, that there would that Night be great numbers of Noble-men, and Gentlemen of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, from all the parts of the Kingdom, in that Town, who with himſelf had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to take the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and poſſeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of all his Majeſties Ammunition there, to morrow morning, being <hi>Saturday;</hi> and that they intended firſt to batter the Chimnies, and if the City would not yield, then to batter down the Houſes, and ſo cut off all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants that would not joyn with them. And that the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> then told him, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> had prepared men in all parts of the Kingdom, to deſtroy all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting there, to morrow Morning by ten a Clock; and that the Proteſtants in all the Sea-Ports, and other Towns
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47823:6"/>in the Kingdom ſhould be killed this Night; and that all the Poſts that could be, could not prevent it; that he moved the ſaid <hi>Hugh</hi> to forbear executing of that Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to diſcover it for the ſaving of his own Eſtate, who ſaid he could not help it. But ſaid, they did owe their Allegiance to the King, and would Pay him all his Rights, but that they did this for the Tyrannical Government, that was over them, and to imitate <hi>Scotland,</hi> who got a Priviledge by that courſe. This is the main Scope of the firſt Examination that was taken before the Lords Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which occaſioned the following Proclamation.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="proclamation">
               <body>
                  <head>By the Lords Juſtices and Council.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>W. Parſons. John Borlaſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THeſe are to make known and publiſh to all His Majeſties good Subjects in this Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>that there is a Diſcovery made by Us the Lords Juſtices and Council, of a moſt diſloyal and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Conſpiracy intended by ſome evil-affected</hi> Iriſh <hi>Papiſts, againſt the lives of Us the Lords Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Council, and many other of His Majeſties faithful Subjects, univerſally throughout this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and for the ſeizing not only of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47823:6"/>Caſtle of</hi> Dublin, <hi>His Majeſties principal Fort here, but alſo of the other Fortifications in the Kingdom: And ſeeing by the great goodneſs and abundant Mercy of Almighty God to His Majeſty, and this State and Kingdom, thoſe wicked Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies are brought to Light, and ſome of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators committed to the Caſtle of</hi> Dublin, <hi>by Us, by His Majeſties Authority, ſo as thoſe wicked and damnable Plots are now diſappointed in the chief parts thereof: We therefore have thought fit hereby, not only to make it publickly known, for the comfort of His Majeſties good and loyal Subjects in all parts of the Kingdom, but alſo hereby to require them, that they do with all confidence and chearfulneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to their own Defence, and ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Guard, ſo to render the more ſafety to themſelves, and all the Kingdom beſides; and that they advertiſe Us with all poſſible ſpeed of all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents, which may concern the Peace and Safety of the Kingdom, and now to ſhew fully that Faith and Loyalty, which they have always ſhown for the publick ſervices of the Crown and Kingdom, which We will value to His Majeſty accordingly, and a ſpecial memory thereof will be retained for their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in due time. And We require that great care be taken that no Levies of men be made for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47823:7"/>Forreign Service, nor any men ſuffered to March upon any ſuch pretence. Given at His Majeſties Caſtle of</hi> Dublin, <hi>Octob.</hi> 23. 1641.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. Dillon. Ro. Digby. Ad. Loftus. J. Temple. Tho. Rotheram. Fr. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loughby. Ja. Ware. Ro. Meridith.</signed> 
                     <hi>God ſave the King.</hi>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Before we come to the Particulars of this bloody Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, it will not be amiſs to recite a paſſage from the Excellent Pen, of that great Peer and States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the Earl of <hi>Orrery,</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>P. Welſh.</hi> The Wifeſt of men thought the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts faſtened to his Majeſty in the Year, 1641. by the beſt of Governments, and to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants, by the ſtricteſt tyes of Intereſt and Friendſhip, Marriage, and which is more in their Eſteem, Goſſiping and Feaſting; to the publick Peace, by their, as flouriſhing, ſo free Condition; and to all, by thoſe Royal Graces, which his Sacred Majeſty at that time Indulged their Commiſſioners; ſuch as themſelves deſired, 'twas but to Ask and have: Yet all this Honey was turn'd into Gall; for at that very time, wherein the King was Exerciſing ſuch High Acts of Grace to them, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts Plotted, and ſoon after perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated the worſt of Rebellions; the worſt Extenſive, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulcerating generally; and Intenſive, breaking forth, with more Perfidy, Barbariſme and Cruelty, than can be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel'd in any Hiſtory. So far that extraordinary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>But whilſt by the great Care and Conduct of the Lords Juſtices, and Council, the intended ſurprize of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47823:7"/>the Caſtle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> was defeated, divers of the Chief Ring-Leaders ſeized and in Cuſtody, their other Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates brake forth in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted and Tragick Execution of their Helliſh Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; and dividing their Forces into ſeveral Parties, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording, as they had determined amongſt themſelves, at one time ſurprized by Treachery, the Town and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the <hi>Newry,</hi> the Fort of <hi>Don-Gannon,</hi> the Fort <hi>Mont-Joy, Charl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>, Ton-Rages, Carick, Mac-Roſſe, Clough-Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Caſtle <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ley,</hi> Caſtle of <hi>Monagham;</hi> being all of them conſiderable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>es of ſtrength, and in divers of them Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe and Foot, belonging to the ſtanding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. They likewiſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de themſelves Maſters of a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of other Caſtles, Houſes of ſtrength, Towns and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages well Peopled with <hi>Engliſh</hi> Inhabitants, who had much inriched the Country as well as themſelves, by their painful Labours. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> thought themſelves ſecare in the friendſhip of their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tenants, Servants or Land-Lords, and the ſurrounding Neighbourhood, whom they had endeavoured to oblige by all the kindneſſes of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: So that when the Fire firſt began to break out, and the whole Country began to riſe about them, ſome had their recourſe to thoſe they eſteemed their Friends, for Protection, relying on their Tenants, Neighbours, or Land-lords for Preſervation, or at leaſt preſent ſafety, and with great confidence, put their Lives, their Wives, their Children, and all they had into their Power. But Oh Inhumane and Perfidious! theſe confiding Innocents, were by theſe their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Friends, either betrayed into the hands of other Rebels, or moſt inhumanely Butcher'd by their own hands; ſuch Maxims had their bloody Prieſts inſtilled into them, that they held it mortal ſin to give any manner of relief or Protection to the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> No tyes of Faith or Friendſhip, could reſtrain their Rage: <hi>Iriſh</hi> Landlords devoured their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tenants; <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tenants and Servants made a Sacrifice of their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Landlords and Maſters; one Neighbour cruelly Butchered and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47823:8"/>another: the Venom deſcended in the Veins of their Children; thoſe of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nation, in the very beginning fell to Strip and Kill the Children of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> 'Twas thought meritorious in them that could by any means bring the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to Deſtruction; Servants were killed as they were Plowing in the Fields; Husbands cut to peices in the preſence of their Wives; the Childrens Brains daſhed out in the Preſence of their Parents, and in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their Goods and Cattel were ſeized, their Houſes burnt, the Places of their Habitation laid deſolate; and thoſe that had their Lives, expoſed to the greateſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Nakedneſs and Famine.</p>
            <p>Where the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtood upon their Defence, and in ſmall Parties endeavoured to oppoſe the violence of the Rebels, there they entrapt them with promiſes of ſafety of Paſs-ports, of Protections for themſelves and Goods. This they confirmed to them ſometimes by Oaths and deepeſt Proteſtations, ſometimes under Hand and Seal; but no ſooner were they in their Power, but they took themſelves to be diſcharged from the Sacred Obligations of Faith and Juſtice, and with more than Pagan Barbariſm, cut in peices thoſe whom they had taken into their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection; Permitting their Soldiers after all the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ſecurities, to deſtroy and Butcher them at their Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p>Nor were the ſacred Walls of the Cathedral Church at <hi>Armagh</hi> any defence againſt the Sacrilegious Violences of Sir <hi>Phelim Oneal,</hi> and his Brother <hi>Turner:</hi> Beſides, many others by the ſame Artifices inveigled and betrayed out of Churches, Caſtles, and Places, to which they had fled for ſecurity. The Rebels were embodied and diſperſed in Parties through all the Neighbourhoods, ſo that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> durſt not draw out of their own Houſes, to form a Body to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them: whereas if they had left their Houſes upon the firſt riſing of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and in ſeveral Counties put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a Poſture of Defence, they might have undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47823:8"/>prevented the effuſion of much of that Blood which for want of ſome ſuch Conduct, was ſo barborouſly ſpilt. Other Policies they made uſe of, to heighten and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the Calamities of the Innocent. Of ſome they took Plate, Money, or whatever other moveables could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; promiſing them under ſuch conſideration to convey them ſafe to <hi>Dublin;</hi> notwithſtanding which, by an unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidented perfidy, they either expoſed them into ſuch unſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable Calamities upon the way, under which they could not ſubſiſt, or elſe diſpatcht them by an immediate But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, after they had undertaken their Conduct.</p>
            <p>At the firſt breaking out, they did not in many places murder many of them; but the courſe they took, was to ſeize upon their Goods and Cattel, and all they could ſtrip them of, leaving themſelves, their Wives, and Children naked, and in that miſerable plight expoſed to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of moſt bitter Cold and Hunger; forcing many of them to the Mountains, to ſeek their way through Woods and Boggs; and if by any means they procured other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, ſo but of Rags, they were immediately ſtript of that too, and none ſuffer'd to give them any ſhelter or relief, without falling under the heavy diſpleaſure of their Prieſts and Officers.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Creighton,</hi> who by his Charity relieved great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them, and for that time preſerved them from Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing; teſtifies upon his Examination, that in one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany there paſſed by his Houſe fourteen hundred Perſons, beſides divers other leſſer numbers, all without any Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, or any thing but their Cloaths, which they ſuffer'd them not to carry away with them, but moſt cruelly ſtript many of them to their Skins, and betray'd them into the hands of other Rebels, by whom they were barbarouſly killed or mangled: Thirty Perſons of one Company be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlain out-right, and a hundred and fifty others miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably wounded; ſo that Tracts of Blood iſſuing from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47823:9"/>their Wounds, lay upon the High-way for twelve miles together. Many very young Children, to the number of ſixty or thereabout, were left, and periſhed by the way, becauſe the bloody purſuit of the Rebells were ſuch, that their Parents and Friends could carry them no further. Some of the Cannibals vowed, that if any dug Graves to bury their dead Children, themſelves ſhould be buried therein: So theſe miſerable People were compelled to leave moſt of them unburied, expos'd to ravenous Beaſts and Fowls; ſome few of the diſtreſſed Parents were forced to carry a great way, to cover them with Earth. A Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man great with Child, was left upon the Road ſtripped to her Smock, who was ſet upon by three <hi>Iriſh</hi> Women and ſome Children, who rent and miſerably tore the ſaid poor <hi>Engliſh</hi> Woman, leaving her Naked in a bitter Froſt and Snow; Inſomuch that ſhe fell in Labour under their hands, and both ſhe and her Child died together. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe Men, and Women, and Children, that eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into places of Safety, not long out-lived the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their paſſage, but either with Grief, or weary with Travel, Hunger, Cold and Nakedneſs, contracted thoſe Diſeaſes, which put a Period to their Pilgrimage.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe Outrages, and Deſolations ravaged in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers parts of the Countrey, eſpecially the Northern parts, (for they had not yet diſcovered their united Treaſons in other places,) the Lords Juſtices, and Council, iſſued a Commiſſion of Fire and Sword, for the deſtruction of the Rebels and their Aſſociates, and withal to receive as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them as would ſubmit to Mercy into his Majeſties Favour: They likewiſe gave out what quantities of Arms and other Ammunition the preſent Exigences would af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, to preſerve the Peace, and obſtruct the Irruption of the yet undiſcovered Flames, which were ready to breakforth in the neareſt adjoyning Counties to the City of <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin:</hi> Theſe Commiſſions and Arms were put into the hands of the Popiſh Nobility and Gentry, who pretended great
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47823:9"/>Loyalty and affection to the Publick, as well as into the hands of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> By which it is apparent, the great Confidence the Lords-Juſtices and Council were pleaſed to Repoſe in them, ſeeking by this means to have made them Inſtrumental for the Preſervation of much of that Blood, and many of thoſe Lives, which notwithſtanding all their endeavours were overwhelmed by the Uncontroulable torrent of that Bloody Rebellion; which now no longer confines it ſelf within the Limits of the Northern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but brake out in the Neighbourhood of the Chief City, about the middle of <hi>November.</hi> The Barbarous <hi>Iriſh</hi> in the County of <hi>Wiclow,</hi> moſt furiouſly fell upon the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> Robbing, Pillaging, Murdering all within that Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; their fair Houſes were ſoon conſumed to Aſhes, their Cattel and live Goods drove away, and a ſiege laid to Fort <hi>Carew,</hi> wherein was a Company of Foot belonging to the old Army.</p>
            <p>In few days after, this Conſpiracy ſhewed it ſelf in the Counties of <hi>Wexford</hi> and <hi>Caterlagh,</hi> who equalled if not exceeded the bloody Cauelties of their Neighbours. Likewiſe the County of <hi>Kildare,</hi> into whoſe hands the State had intruſted Arms and Munition for the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Publick, even thoſe Arms ſo deſign'd, were employed againſt them; nor was the Carriage of the Lords and Chief Gentlemen of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pale, ſuch as exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from ſuſpicion. This indeed was that which heightned the fears and apprehenſions of the City of <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> which was now the only Sanctuary of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they ſaw themſelves ſurrounded with the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Troops of Inhumane Rebels on every quarter. But that which added the greateſt Terror to their Conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was the conſtant Reſort of multitudes who came in every moment ſtripped, wounded and miſerably deſtroyed from the Northern parts: Perſons who had lived in good Quality, having no covering but Rags; others wrapt round with twiſted Straw, to hide their Nakedneſs; here you ſhould ſee ſome Reverend Miniſters, and others of a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47823:10"/>grave Aſpect, bruiſed, hackt and wounded, and hardly eſcaping with their Lives; nothing was heard but the ſad Lamentations of Wives for their murdered Husbands, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for their Children barbarouſly Butchered before their Faces; Poor Infants, batter'd and benumm'd with Cold and Travel, gaſping out their Souls in the Boſoms of their Fainting Mothers.</p>
            <p>So great were the numbers of thoſe that periſhed in the Churches, Streets, and Corners of the City, that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Burying-places could not contain them: Two large Pieces of Ground were ſet apart for that purpoſe, theſe were never to be forgotten Objects of Teſtimonies of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Commiſeration. It is not eaſie to form an Idea of the diſmal Confuſion and Conſternation which ſhewed it ſelf in the Faces of the diſtracted Citizens; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants ſaw thoſe Barbarities, Out-rages, and Slaughters, which had fallen upon their Country-men in Adjacent parts, now entring in at their own Gates; the Papiſts Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, furniſhed with Arms ready to execute their Conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Villanies, themſelves fenceleſs, without Fortification or other means to ſecure them from their Barbarous At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts; ſuch a frightful Aſpect ſhewed it ſelf in the City, as ſeemed an Omen of their approaching Ruine. Nor was it only the Common and Inferiour ſort that were the Actors in theſe diſmal Tragedies, but ſome of the Chief Gentlemen of the Nation, under pretence of ſecuring the Goods of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> took them into their own Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, without any deſign of ever making any Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but having after this peaceable ſort deprived them of their ſubſiſtence, they afterward expoſed them to the want of all things, without reſtoring any part of their own to be a Refreſhment to them in their great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities.</p>
            <p>Many of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants had entertained ſo good an Opinion of their being kindly dealt with, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered their Goods into their hands by Retail, giving them Inventories of all they had; they took ſome of the choiceſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47823:10"/>Goods out of places wherein they had concealed them, to put them into the Cuſtody of the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> who having, as hath been ſaid, either by force or fraud made themſelves Maſters of the Proteſtants Eſtates, next ſpared not to ſtrip Man, Woman and Child, and expoſe them to the ſeverity of the Weather, in many places not permitting them the ſhelter of a Buſh, or to remain in the Woods; forbidding thoſe of their own Nation and Communion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great Penalties to give them any ſort of Entertainment or Relief.</p>
            <p>And perhaps amongſt all their Barbarities none look with a blacker Face, or gives a truer Demonſtration of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placableneſs of their Temper, and their natural thirſt for Blood, then this carriage of theirs, that thoſe who periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not under the violence of their hands, ſhould notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be expoſed to ſuch rigours and inſuperable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, as they were not able to out-live: they were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to have ſtript them once or twice, but as often as they got any covering, thô never ſo tattered and miſerable, the next <hi>Iriſh</hi> Woman, nay even their very Children, would not fail to ſtrip them of them; of which divers Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were given in before the Commiſſioners, in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half appointed, eſpecially one <hi>John Courley,</hi> Depoſeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Examination, That when the Town of <hi>Armagh</hi> was ſet on Fire by the Rebels; and his Wife joyned in the ſame Depoſition, That their Houſe being conſumed in that Conflagration, ſhe was ſtript no leſs then ſeven ſeveral times, and at laſt left with not ſo much as her Smock or Hair-lace; and that ſhe concealed her ſelf in her Hutch for three or four dayes, and then went to ſeek her Children, two of which had the Small-Pox at that time appearing upon them: This was an infallible way to accompliſh their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane and Bloody purpoſes, as was too viſible by the Iſſue; the High-wayes and Towns through which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had paſſed, being covered with heaps of thoſe which had periſhed of that great Mortality, which was the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the Inhumane Cruelty of the Bloody Rebels:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47823:11"/>For a further Confirmation of which, take the following Depoſitions.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>James Refern,</hi> of the County of <hi>London-Derry;</hi> which gives an Account, that in the Town of <hi>Colerain,</hi> the Mortality was ſo great, that the Living were hardly capable of ſtowing the Bodies of the Dead, which they pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kt in great Ranks, in large Graves or Holes, as if they had been packing Herrings.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>Magdalen Redman,</hi> is no leſs to the purpoſe, which ſaith, That a great Company of her Protaſtant Neighbours, amongſt which were twenty two Widows, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been robb'd and ſtript ſtark naked, they covered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Houſe with Straw, which ſome of the Rebels ſet a Fire, on purpoſe to burn or ſmother them; but ſome of them being touched with more Compaſſion, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to forbear, by which they eſcaped that fiery Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al: Notwithſtanding which they were driven naked into the Woods, where they were forced to continue in Froſt and Snow, from Tueſday to Saturday, their Bodies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo Cold, that the Snow lay upon them unmelted, divers of their Children dying in their Arms: When they endeavoured to eſcape to the <hi>Burre,</hi> the wicked Rebels would turn them towards <hi>Dublin,</hi> and when they were making for <hi>Dublin,</hi> they hindered them again, telling them they ſhould to the <hi>Burre.</hi> Thus were they toſſed from place to place where there was no ſhelter, nor any relief; ſo that many of them dyed under their hands; and of thoſe that after eſcaped to the <hi>Burre,</hi> though they there met with ſome Relief, by the Charity of <hi>William Parſons</hi> Eſquire, yet above forty of their number died there, of the Cruelty they had undergone.</p>
            <p>In the Caſtle of <hi>Liſgoole,</hi> a hundred fifty two Men, Women, and Children, were burnt or ſmothered, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by Depoſition, of <hi>Tho. Wenſlaw,</hi> and <hi>John Simpſon.</hi> At the Caſtle of <hi>Moneah,</hi> ninety Proteſtants were ſlain and murdered: the ſame Rebels having promiſed fair Quarter to the Proteſtants in the Caſtle of <hi>Tallah,</hi> after
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47823:11"/>they had the Caſtle and their Arms delivered into their hands, firſt ſtript them of all they had, and then moſt barbarouſly murder'd them. This was atteſted by <hi>Tho. Wenſlaw</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>One hundred Perſons, moſt of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Nation, were hanged or otherwiſe deſtroyed at <hi>Liſſenskeah;</hi> where <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mac Guire</hi> with his Company, having in a pretended friendly manner deſired to ſpeak with one Mr. <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> who had the keeping of the Caſtle, being Clerk of the Peace, and upon that, the ſecuring the Records of the Countrey; theſe the ſaid <hi>Mac Guire</hi> having enforc'd <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleton</hi> to deliver to him, immediately burnt: Taking like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a Thouſand pound in Money, which he had of Sir <hi>William Balfoures:</hi> after which he compelled Mr. <hi>Middleton</hi> to hear Maſs, and to ſwear never to alter from it, and then with a Compaſſion equally extending to Soul and Body, cauſed both Him, his Wife and Children to be hung up, and immediately ſtrangled.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Portnedown Bridge,</hi> ſo famous for the never to be forgotten Cruelties of the ſavage Rebels, a thouſand Men, Women and Children were in ſeveral Parties unmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thrown into the River; for they having broken the Bridge down in the midſt, forced the miſerable Innocents to expire in thoſe Waters: Some Relations ſpeak of four thouſand perſons that were drowned in that County. The Barbarous Wretches drove the Poor pillaged Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them like Herds of Swine, wounding, pricking and forcing them forwards with their Swords, and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Cruelty; and if they ſlackned their Pace, they were either knockt on the Head, or thrown over into the River.</p>
            <p>To divers, and very conſiderable Companies, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to give Paſſes of ſafe Conduct under the Hand of that Arch-Rebel Sir <hi>Phelim O Neal,</hi> and when they had brought them near ſome great River, or place fit for their Purpoſe, they failed not to caſt them into the Water; and if any endeavoured to make their eſcape, they were
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47823:12"/>knock't on the Head with Poles, or ſhot with Piſtols, or other fire-arms, to prevent the ſaving of their wretched Lives.</p>
            <p>It's very Obſervable, what in this diſmal Hiſtory is mention'd, of one Mrs. <hi>Cambel,</hi> who being by them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the River, and perceiving no means to eſcape their Fury, ſuddenly claſpt her Arms about one of their Chiefs, who was moſt forward to thruſt her into the Water, and carried him down with her to the Bottom, where they both periſhed together.</p>
            <p>So great was the inveterate Rage of that Sir <hi>Phelim O Neal,</hi> that he cauſed another conſiderable Rebel to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon together the Proteſtants remaining about <hi>Armagh,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Conduct them to <hi>Colerain,</hi> and when they were got hardly one dayes Journey from him, they were all Butcher'd and deſtroyed, as many others were by Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from his Brother: By their Order likewiſe, the Aged People were taken out of <hi>Armagh,</hi> and murdered at <hi>Charlemont;</hi> ſoon after which they ſet fire to the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral and Town of <hi>Armagh,</hi> where they deſtroyed above five hundred Perſons, Young and Old. Forty eight Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies at the Pariſh of <hi>Keblaman,</hi> were Barbarouſly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by Direction from the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim,</hi> after they had been protected by him three quarters of a Year.</p>
            <p>Within two Miles of <hi>Kilmore,</hi> there were two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants burnt in one houſe; and the Rebels ſtrip't, kill'd, or murdered all, or the moſt of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in that Pariſh, which conſiſted of two hundred Families: they likewiſe ſet many in the Stocks, that would not Confeſs their Money, and when they had all they could get, then they Murdered them.</p>
            <p>Many other Horrid Inhumane Cruelties were uſed in the murdering of Multitudes of poor Innocent Souls. To many theſe bloody Villains ſhewed ſo much favour as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly to diſpatch them out of their Pain, by no means allowing them leave or time to make their Prayers! for
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47823:12"/>others they held a ſudden Death too eaſie a Puniſhment: Therefore they Impriſon'd ſome in moſt beaſtly Dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, full of Dirt and Mire, and there Clapping bolts on their Heels, ſuffered them to periſh at leiſure. Others they barbrouſly mangled and left Languiſhing upon the High-wayes, crying out for ſo much Mercy as to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered out of their Pain. Others they buryed alive, a manner of Death they uſed to ſeveral of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in ſeveral places. An Engliſh-man, his Wife, four or five Children, and a Maid, were hang'd, and afterwards put all into one Hole; the Youngeſt Child being not fully dead, put out the Hand, and crying, <hi>Mammy, Mammy,</hi> when without Mercy they buryed him alive.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Clowms,</hi> within the County of <hi>Fermanagh,</hi> there were ſeventeen, having been hanged till they were half dead, caſt together into a Pit, and being covered over with a little Earth, lay Pittifully ſending out moſt lamentable Groans for a good time after. Some were deadly wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo hanged upon Tenter-hooks. Some had Ropes put about their Necks, and ſo drawn through the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſome had Withs, and ſo drawn up and down thorow Woods and Bogs; others were hanged up and taken down, and hanged up ſeveral times, and all to make them confeſs their Money, which as ſoon as they told, they then diſpatcht them out of the way. Others were hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the Arms, and with many ſlaſhes and cuts they made the Experiment with their Swords, how many blows an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> would endure before he dyed. Some had their Bellies Ript up, and ſo left with their Guts run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning about their Heels. But this kind of Cruelty was principally reſerved by theſe Inhumane Monſters for the Women, whoſe Sex they neither pitied nor ſpared, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ſeveral Women, many of them great with Child, whoſe Bellies they ript up as they hung, and ſo let the little Infants fall out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A courſe they often took with them they found in that ſad Condition. And ſometimes they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47823:13"/>gave their Children to Swine; ſome the Dogs eat; and ſome taken alive out of their Mothers Bellies, they caſt into Ditches. And for ſucking Children, and others of a Riper Age, ſome had their Brains knock't out, others were trampled under foot to Death.</p>
            <p>Some of the Rebels meeting one Mrs. <hi>Howard,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Frankland,</hi> both great with Child, and ſix of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with them, with their Pikes killed and murdered them all, and after ripped open the Gentlewomens Bellies, took out their Children, and threw them into a Ditch. Some they cut in Goblets and Pieces, others they Ript up alive. Some were found in the Fields ſucking the Breaſts of their murdered Mothers. Others lay ſtifled in Vaults and Cellars, others ſtarved in Caves, crying out to their Mothers rather to ſend them out to be kill'd by the Rebels, than to ſuffer them to ſtarve there.</p>
            <p>One <hi>Mary Barlow</hi> depoſeth up Oath, That Her Husband being hanged by the Rebels before her Face, ſhe and ſix Children were ſtripped ſtark Naked, and turn'd out a begging in Froſt and Snow, by means whereof they were almoſt ſtarved, having nothing to Eat in three Weeks, while they lay in a Cave, but two old Calf-skins, which they beat with Stones, and ſo eat them, hair and all: Multitudes of Men, Women and Children were found drowned, caſt into Ditches, Bogs, and Turf-Pits, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Sepulchres of the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Nation. Thouſands dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of cold and want in all parts of the Countrey, being neither permitted to depart, nor relieved where they were enforced to ſtay. Multitudes encloſed in Houſes, which being ſet on fire, they were there moſt miſerably conſumed; ſome dragg'd out of their Sick-beds to the place of Execution: Such was the barbarous and inhumane Cruelty of the Rebels, that ſometimes they enforced the Wife to kill the Husband, the Son to kill the Father, and the Daughter to kill the Mother, and then they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47823:13"/>world hang or put to Death the laſt Bloodſhedder.</p>
            <p>In the Town of <hi>Slego,</hi> they forced one <hi>Lears</hi> the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to kill his Father, and then hanged the Son: and in <hi>Mogne</hi> they forced one <hi>Simon Lepers</hi> Wife to kill her Husband, and then cauſed her Son to kill her, and then they hanged the Son. Children were enforced to carry their Aged Parents to the places deſigned for their Slaughter, Mothers to caſt their own Children into the Water, and yet after theſe enforced Acts, which no doubt were performed, out of Hopes and Aſſurance to have their own Lives ſaved, alwayes Murdered. And ſuch was the Malice, and moſt deteſtable hatred born to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> as they taught their Children to kill <hi>Engliſh</hi> Children, and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Women did na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally expreſs as much Cruelty, as the chiefeſt Rebels among them. If theſe be not ſufficient, let us look over the particular Ends of ſome particular Perſons, and we ſhall in them behold more Horrid Cruelties than theſe before mentioned. What ſhall we ſay to a Child boyl'd to Death in a Cauldron, being the Child of one <hi>Tho. Straton</hi> of <hi>Newtown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Woman hanged on a Tree, and in the Hair of her Head her own Daughter hanged up with her. A Woman miſerably Rent and Torn to pieces. Some ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Rebels, their Eyes pluckt out, their Hands cut off, and ſo turn'd out to wander up and down; others ſtoned to Death. A Man wounded, and ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in a hole digged in the Earth, and ſo covered up to the very Chin, there left in that miſerable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to Pine and periſh. A Mans Feet held in the Fire till he was burnt to Death, his Wife hanged at his Door. A Miniſter ſtript ſtark naked, and ſo dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven like a Beaſt through the Town of <hi>Caſhel,</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47823:14"/>following him, and pricking him forward with Darts and Rapiers.</p>
            <p>A Company of Men, Women and Children, put into a Houſe, and as they were burning, ſome Children that made an eſcape out of the Flames, were taken by ſome of the Rebels who ſtood by, cut them in pieces with Sithes, and ſo caſt them into the Fire again.</p>
            <p>Neither did theſe Horrible Tortures, which they put theſe Innocent Chriſtians unto, a-ſlake their Fury, their Malice towards them did not Determine with their Breath.</p>
            <p>But after ſo many ſeveral Bloody Wayes and cruel Inventions, wherewith they rent their Souls from their wretched Bodies, extended even to their dead Carcaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: In ſome places they denyed all manner of Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; ſome they caſt into Ditches, others they left to be devoured by Dogs and Swine, others by Fowls and Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Birds. Nay ſeveral which had been formerly bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, they digg'd up, and left them to putrifie above ground.</p>
            <p>And theſe truly are but ſome of thoſe wayes among many others, which with moſt exquiſite pains, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Tortures were uſed by theſe mercileſs Rebels, to let in Death among an Innocent, unreſiſting People, that had alwayes lived Peaceably with them; Adminiſtring all manner of Helps and Comforts to thoſe who were in Diſtreſs, that made no difference betwixt them and thoſe of their own Nation, but ever Cheriſhed them as Friends, and Loving Neighbours, without giving any cauſe of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs or diſtaſte unto them.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:47823:14"/>
            <p>It is not poſſible to recollect or expreſs the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their miſchievous Inventions, or horrour of their bloody Executions, actuated with all kind of circumſtances that might aggravate the heighth of their Cruelty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. Alas! who can comprehend the fears, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, anguiſh, bitterneſs and perplexity of their Souls? the deſpairing Paſſions and Conſternations of their Minds? What ſtrange amazed Thoughts muſt it needs raiſe in their ſad Hearts, to find themſelves ſo ſuddenly ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed without remedy, and inextricably wrapt up in all kind of outward miſeries which could poſſibly by man be inflicted upon any humane Creatures! What ſighs, groans, trembling, aſtoniſhment! what ſcrieches, cryes, and bitter lamentation of Wife, Children, Friends and Servants, howling and weeping about them, all finding themſelves without any manner of hope of deliverance from their preſent Miſery and Pain! how inexorable were their barbarous Tormentors, that compaſſed them on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, without all bowels of compaſſion, any ſence of their Sufferings, or the leaſt commiſeration or pity, the common Comforters of men in Miſery. It was no ſmall addition to their ſorrows, to hear the baſe reviling ſpeeches uſed againſt their Countrey and Countrey-men, ſome loudly threatning all ſhould be cut off and utterly deſtroyed, that had one drop of <hi>Engliſh</hi>-blood in them: The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Women crying out, to ſpare neither Man, Woman, nor Child, that was <hi>Engliſh;</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> was meat for Dogs, and their Children Baſtards.</p>
            <p>How grievous and inſupportable muſt it needs be to a true Chriſtian ſoul, to hear a baſe villain boaſt, that his hands were ſo weary with killing and knocking down Proteſtants into a Bogg, that he could not lift his Arms up to his Head? or others to ſay, that they had killed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47823:15"/>ſo many <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, that the greaſe or fat which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained on their Swords or Skeins, might have made an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Candle! Or to conſider, that two young Cow-boys ſhould have it in their Power to murder thirty ſix Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants! whoſoever ſhall ſeriouſly weigh theſe Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, will not much wonder that ſo great numbers of <hi>Brittiſh</hi> and Proteſtants ſhould be deſtroyed in ſo ſhort a time after the firſt breaking out of the Rebellion: As Mr. <hi>Cunningham</hi> Depoſeth in his Examination, he there ſaith, that the Account of the Perſons killed by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, from the time of the beginning of the Rebellion, <hi>October</hi> 23. 1641. unto the Month of <hi>April</hi> following, was, as the Prieſts weekly gave it in, in their ſeveral Pariſhes, one hundred and five thouſand, <hi>April</hi> 22. 1642.</p>
            <p>When the Caſtle of <hi>Liſgoole</hi> was ſet on fire by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and ſo many <hi>Brittiſh</hi> as are before mentioned, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in the flames, thoſe miſchievous Villains that had done that wicked Fact, cryed out with much Joy, <hi>How ſweetly do they fry!</hi> How did the Inhabitants of <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> a City planted with old <hi>Engliſh,</hi> where Civility and good Manners ſeemed to flouriſh, ſolace and pleaſe themſelves in abuſing moſt unchriſtianly the Heads of a Miniſter and ſix other Proteſtants, brought in a kind of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph into the Town! Certainly it is not to be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, much leſs expreſſed, with what ſcorn and deriſion they acted theſe great Crueities upon all <hi>Brittiſh</hi> which they had gotten into their Power! with what Joy and Exultation their Eyes did behold the ſad ſpectacle of their Miſeries! what greedy delight and pleaſure they took in their bloody Executions! what Malice and Hatred they expreſſed towards them! many with the laſt ſtroke of Death giving them, in their laſt Agony, that fearful Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lediction in <hi>Iriſh, Anim a Duel,</hi> Thy Soul to the Devil.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:47823:15"/>
            <p>But it is no wonder that they carried themſelves after this barbarous manner to theſe poor Chriſtians, when they ſpared not moſt fearfully to belch out their Rage againſt their Maker. What open Helliſh Blaſphemies were uttered by theſe wicked Miſcreants! With what Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Reproach did they tear and trample under feet the ſacred <hi>Word of God?</hi> How diſpitefully did they upbraid the Profeſſion of the Truth, to thoſe bleſſed Souls, whom neither by Threats nor Terrors, pains nor Torments, they could draw to forſake their Religion.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not here touch any further upon thoſe who died thus Gloriouſly, this will be a work fitter for ſome more able Pen.</p>
            <p>If we ſhall take a ſurvey of the Primitive Times, and look into the ſufferings of the Firſt Chriſtians, that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered under the Tyranny and Cruel Perſecutions of thoſe Heatheniſh Emperours, we ſhall not certainly find any one Kingdom, though of a far larger Continent, where more Chriſtians ſuffered, or more unparallel'd Cruelties were act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in many years upon them, than were in <hi>Ireland,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of the firſt two Months after the breaking out of this Rebellion. And howſoever ſome by outward Inflictions and Tortures, were drawn to profeſs the change of their Religion, and had preſently their Reward; (for many of thoſe they ſuddenly diſpatch't with great ſcorn, ſaying, <hi>It was fit to ſend them out of the World in that good Mood;</hi>) yet I dare ſay, we ſhall find many thus Crue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly put to Death, equal to ſome of thoſe Ancient Worthies for their Patience, Conſtancy, Courage, Magnanimity in their ſufferings, but triumphing and inſulting with their laſt breath, over the Inſolency, Rage and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lice of their moſt Inhumane and Cruel Perſecutors.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:47823:16"/>
            <p>We ſhall find in the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory, during the ſeveral Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Conteſtations betwixt <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Scilla,</hi> when their Factious Followers filled the whole City of <hi>Rome</hi> with ſtreams of blood, ſtrange and moſt incomparable Paſſages of Friendſhips: One expoſing himſelf to all manner of Dangers, for the Preſervation of his Friend of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Faction; Servants willing to Sacrifice themſelves to ſave the Lives of their Beloved Maſters. But here on the contrary, what open violations of all bonds of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and Friendſhip! no Contracts, no Promiſes obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; Quarter given in the moſt ſolemn manner, with the greateſt Oaths and ſevereſt Execrations, under Hand and Seal, ſuddenly broken. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Landlords making a Prey of their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tenants, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Servants betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Maſters; And every one eſteeming any Act, wherein they could declare their hatred and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice moſt againſt any of the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Nation, as Gallant and cruly Meritorious.</p>
            <p>It is not to be denied, but that the firſt and moſt bloody Executions were made in the Province of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and there they continued longeſt to execute their Rage and Cruelty; yet muſt it alſo be acknowledged, that all the other three Provinces did concur with them, as it were with one common Conſent, to deſtroy and pluck up by the Roots all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> planted throughout the Kingdom; and for this purpoſe they went on, not only Murdering, Stripping and driving out all of them, Men, Women and Children, but they laid waſte their Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Burnt their Evidences, defaced in many places all the Monuments of Civility and Devotion; the Courts and Places of the Engliſh Government; Nay, as ſome of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves expreſs it, they reſolved not to leave them either Name or Poſterity in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:47823:16"/>
            <p>Notwithſtanding what hath been here Related, be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is matter of Fact, and that for brevity's ſake, many particular Inſtances of their Inhuman Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity be omitted; yet have thoſe of that Communion had the Forehead to deny, or Extenuate thoſe monſtrous Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to lay the Guilt of all that Blood upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants themſelves; as if they had been the Contrivers of their own Executions, and of the Extirpation of their own Families; which is an Aſſurance ſo peculiar to the Papiſts, that cannot be matcht amongſt any other ſort of Men, I was about to ſay <hi>Monſters.</hi> Theſe are proofs of that Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity, and Charity, that Humanity and Sincerity, which is to be expected from thoſe, the Principles of whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, teach them to ſtick at no Villany, no Butchery, no Perjury, nor Cruelty, for the promoting their Bloody Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
